[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, his restraint was like denial of the entire domain of the senses, not just restraint in regard to the unwholesome, in regard to sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was like the simile of the bait, that sutta, where you kind of completely shun the bait, you shun everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the danger, but you can't, like, stay within it, you know, in a careful manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cut deep, you throw the whole thing away.
[SPEAKER_01]: In sooner or later, you have to come back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like when people, like, you just strain, sort of restrain, and then just, poof, give in, and then, you know, the dam breaks, and then just create worse mess than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh, so it's kind of oscillating between those two ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I, in that talk, when I said, you know, like a, like, say, like your senses, say, a visual sense, it's like a wild dog, that wants to be courier.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes, okay, by default, you resist the pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sometimes, you can't constantly be resisting the pull, because it will wear you down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you have to pick your battles.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you resist the pull, there is clearly unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no negotiation there.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, if that wild dog is pulling you towards something that is neutral,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be careful to let, like, not resist that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's easy to give in and say, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like what monks usually do when they ordain or something and they come and that's when they become neurotic.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, vinaya, vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, vinaya actually says the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but still.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, but still.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to allow for that space in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the whole thing with the way that we spoke before, with like, putting the cloth down in women, it's actually not properly seen before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can exactly see how it originated, was from
[SPEAKER_01]: A woman might have accidentally brushed against your fingers when you were receiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the vinaya says clearly, if that thing happens, it's not an offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You did not intend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, you know, a doubtful mind, well, a mind that is not developed in regard to doubt, will be overwhelmed by that doubt eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you know that really you haven't done anything wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Vinaya says that you haven't done anything wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was unintentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't sleep at night, because basically you're caught in this neurotic, kind of doubting, paranoid, sort of... whatever, spiraling out of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, what you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you, like, make an extra step and you create your own rule and... to prevent even that from happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll put a cloth down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll put a cloth, so then the woman can't touch me accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but being touched accidentally is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that is bothering you, you should deal with that on that phenomenological level, not like on the level of running away and imposing another rule on top of a rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that rule is unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most certainly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it can be relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you use a cloth or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, in this case, for example, it actually goes against the vinaya rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because of your neurosis, vinaya became inadequate for you, and you need more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is exactly what happens in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: The core of art.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sense of seeing a wild dog that's pulling me out, that's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Problem is, when it ends up in unwholesome states, and then I have to suffer and counter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same wild dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never was mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never can be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you just basically foresee the unwholesome scenarios where that dog will go, and you prevent that, and then let it go, and then the dog will eventually calm down as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you mustn't go around just saying no to everything you see, everything you hear, everything that you might doubt, because you might doubt everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's just going to be a very tight and unpleasant state, and it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no exception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people do suffer, on the contrary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even when you say, you have to avoid unwholesome, don't necessarily worry about wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite hard for them to allow that, because that literally means taking up responsibility for the distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, now I have to rely on my own criteria, that this is unwholesome and this is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no external authority, there is no external community, external monastery, external vinaya, external this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of beforehand, but now, I actually need to draw a line between good and between the bad, and then stay behind that line.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically a very hard thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if a person does that, then they truly go beyond sīla-vāt-paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sīla-vāt-paramāsa, as I'm sure I've said before, it's not what people commonly think of rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some ridiculous bowing to a gold-gilded shrine or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's holding to virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is quite a serious thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As things that will actually free you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: As things that are directly resulting in liberation, which they don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you believe that your virtue and duty will directly lead you to nirvana.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It couldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can enable you to draw a line.
[SPEAKER_01]: The line I was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you draw that line, then virtue and duty, which you have adopted beforehand, and you have to be there, you have to adopt it beforehand,
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you draw a line, once you got the criteria for that line, it falls away, as virtue, as duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it is beyond the sīla, sotāpanna and then eventually arānta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's hard for people to draw that line, because it relies on your own judgment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, there is no safety of tradition, safety of the history, the order of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you, basically, sticking behind what you chose to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you won't be able to wholesomely, or rather rightly, draw that line, if you haven't been adopting, even externally, these rites and rituals, or rather virtue and duty, the norms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you must certainly not stay there, because then, yeah, then you will be like, you know, a fifty-fifty Vāsa monk who is still as neurotic about his rule as on the first day, and still not in the sotā.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's a... going beyond sīla means going deeper.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, going beyond sīla means basically not depending on it, but not breaking it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, being unable to break it, to an extent, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, that sīla is also defined in regard to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas in sīla, I mean, like, all the necessary little... all the little circumstantial vinaya rules, I talk about the basic principles of, you know, celibacy, lying, stealing, things that are, in themselves, unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that is the importance of it, because obviously, you know, virtue is important, but then people take it, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: Even after, you know, all the knowledge you might have gained through suttas or whatever, they're still unable to let go of it, because they don't know they should.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, they fear if they let go, it means they go the opposite of non-sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can happen if that sīla hasn't been established beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it was...
[SPEAKER_01]: So there is that... You have to... Basically, it's like building up a ship, developing sails, you know, gathering all the information about the design and engineering it, and then doing the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, never putting it into water and trying it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never, like, setting it to go, to see if it's gonna sink.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, start sinking, quickly pull it back, repair it, but you have to cross the other shore, not remain on this, clutching onto your little boat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what's the use of the boat if you don't actually use it to sail away into the sea?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of the food, that's like the... that's quite a point that you've seen that yourself, probably experienced that yourself in the monasteries, how people like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, I have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, you know, sexual implications or other unwholesome things that you don't have to do and you shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the food I have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, you always have preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the mouth, your tongue, the sense of taste as an independent animal is an independent animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It prefers things, it wants things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't want certain other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that has kind of evolved completely circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on the stuff you were eating, you develop taste for certain things, you got sick of some other taste, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, for kutujana, it's inseparable from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when somebody says, OK, you need to eat carefully,
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said you have to eat, but you have to eat carefully, like it's your last... you know, you killed your child, you need to eat just for survival.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that is true.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to, like, practice for arhantship, that is absolutely the attitude you have to have.
[SPEAKER_01]: I eat food purely, so this body will still be alive, so that I can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nowhere there does it say you need to be obsessed about your preferences, or certainly try to avoid them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have people who get so wound up, neurotic, about
[SPEAKER_01]: Eating food that they like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I can't be mindful, basically, if the food I'm eating is the food I like.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness has nothing to do with whether what you're eating is what you prefer or what you don't prefer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is actually indifferent to your preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's the mindfulness that makes you correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just the opposite preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I remember that I met people who just intentionally take
[SPEAKER_01]: Opposite of what they really want to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, well, the whole purpose of that is only to avoid responsibility for what you've taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no mindfulness involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you feel responsible if you take what you want to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think you avoid that responsibility by then taking what you don't want to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't see that you're responsible for that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you can't avoid your responsibility by choosing a particular choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, why did I choose what I prefer or what I don't?
[SPEAKER_01]: I am affected by the choice of choosing the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if I write down an impersonal algorithm that calculates for me what number of dishes to take on one day, I have...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have basically chosen the algorithm to be that which can give me the food to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I'm still responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, when you rely on an external thing, an external, like an algorithm, or external written law, or somebody what's said, externally said, you will not be aware internally of your responsibility for your choices, which means you won't be mindful properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize, I think, you don't actually have to fear your preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to fear losing mindfulness in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in regard to animals, that's when the issues set in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when a video gets rekindled and solved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not when you eat your favorite fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people... people might say, I want to give a bit of my attachment towards food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they identify their attachment with their preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Preference is a preference of your taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your taste is not yours, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: That animal is independent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, dragging around for so long, then now you're just... well, you're inseparable from it, in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, your preference is not your attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to preferences, then you're attached, right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing, because people, in the course of their life, got so used to... eating food that you prefer means eating it unmindfully, unwarily, lustfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, now, preference means that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I must avoid presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must stop eating altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like what happened to giants.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could see the revolt, the rebellion of the mind against the preference or the choice, but it went completely the opposite way, within the same domain of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, they just started choosing the opposite, more and more bizarre.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, I will eat every second day.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I will eat every third day.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that becomes
[SPEAKER_01]: Not enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will eat every third day, from every fourth person, on every third junction of the second town.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is completely randomly evolved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heavenly rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And only rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when that basically seems to induce novelty of the restraint... And you find you still lustful for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You just go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then I will stop eating altogether and I will die.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the highest nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, as that certain Buddha said, we were studying in a different context, well, in relation to a different question, when he asked me, why do you think that my disciples respect me?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, because you eat little and you praise it in little, you live under a tree, you praise it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, no, that's not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: I sometimes eat a bowl.
[SPEAKER_01]: full of food up to the brim of the like softest, nicest rice and curries.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I have another bowl full of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he has two alms bowls.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he finishes a full alms bowl of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they ask him, oh, Lord, would you like some?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fill it up again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he eats it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while, at the same time, he has disciples who live... who get food every second day or something, and it's a very coarse and horrible food, and they live covered in like a hemp robes and under a root of tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they were to respect him on account of renouncing behavior, they wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they have the utmost respect for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the dhamma is... well, it's beyond that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they know it because of his teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the respect is unshakable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the Buddha just spent the rest of his days living in king's palaces and eating all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're trying to adjust your food, to adjust your mind, you're taking it from the wrong end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're taking it far enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to solve the problem from a community point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or mix, you know, just mix your food in the bowl.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told you, I was doing that because people were talking about it, and I thought, okay, let's... And I didn't mind, to begin with, but I did find it quite amusing, that on the second day of mixing everything, fish,
[SPEAKER_01]: fruit yogurt, grapes and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: I started developing tastes for certain mixes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I started...
[SPEAKER_01]: I like fish with grapes and... all I... with my mouth is full of all sorts of like... like fruit, curry, rice and... and... and ice cream, whatever was melted over.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if you eat unmindfully, if you lapse, your mind gets focused on the bit of the mouth that is in contact with the taste that you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no end to that separation of your prefer... well, not preference, of your... like, choice, basically, of what you want, what you like, because you can't do that mechanically, because the mind, the sense, will always pick on that, even if you give it... and then, if you just eat what you don't want, within that, you'll start preferring things, like, what you dislike less.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's completely from the wrong end.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you need to do is eat mindfully whatever comes your way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, if you do need a criteria for, okay, but still, what should I eat?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, I'm in a shop as a layman, perhaps, who keeps the precepts, but I'm in a supermarket, I don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what criteria?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, use criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, why do you eat?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do Buddhists say you should eat?
[SPEAKER_01]: To be healthy, so you can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, choose the healthy food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is really horrible tasting healthy food.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is something I really crave about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, either way, choose what's cheaper.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or choose something in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or choose what you like for making a point to not lose the mindfulness while you're eating that which you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if your mindfulness becomes unshakable in regard to harmless preference foods, it's nothing unwholesome about preferring a watermelon over a mango.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: That does not induce lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ignorance in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ignorance in regard to the preferred object that provides you with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what induces lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: But beautiful objects, tasty objects, nice sounds, none of that is actual lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Buddha was quite clear on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, choose whatever you're going to choose for whatever reasons, because that's beside the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, eat it mindfully when you eat it, and be mindful when you finish eating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And never compromise that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, soon enough, it won't take long, if you really commit to that sort of practice, you will basically... you'll stop caring what you eat, because you realize that was never the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, never, never relates to the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was basically appropriating the domain of the taste when you're swallowing the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, entertain the notion that you are actually consuming that food, whereby when that food disappears down your throat, when you swallow it, it's in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That food, when it's in your stomach, it's as external as it was when it was out on the shelf, in the shop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your stomach, then, cannot be appropriated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means the whole domain of your body, then, remains external to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the mindfulness gets established upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that means, you basically, you stepped outside of the whole domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality, the domain whereby pleasure that pertains to senses can't pull you.
[SPEAKER_01]: By being... by stepping outside, they can't pull you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the hollow preferences remain, but none of them induce any lust anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's mindfulness of that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, mind... having your mindfulness established, having your mind composed in regard to that
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in regards to the right extent of that phenomenon of the body, this body here and now... Because most people think like, you know, under your skin it's inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, your lungs are inside, your stomach is, your mouth is kind of inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that inside inevitably has that, like, personal connotations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, for an island, that kind of internal disappears, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's used in a sort of different internal-external, but when the Buddha says what is left, it's this conscious body, I, out there, this conscious lump of flesh in the world, externally, and the name and matter, externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So whichever way he looks, internally or externally, basically all he sees is external and slightly less external, but still external, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean by internal here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be clarified.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because internal is taken as mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering arises, like, you know, the true dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pure dukkha arises internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that, like, sense of mind, you're affected by it.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is regarded as inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you reckon, well, okay, it's inside in relation to what you see from your senses, but all of it, as a whole, it's outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, here, yonder, yonder and here, as in inside, are all other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's all sorts of strange practices, like, yeah... Well, we... At least, because... we're trying to keep, you know, you're suffering in regard to food, in regard to your desires, and so you... you create a view that food is an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you blame the food or you basically, you're so caught up in the desire around the food, you end up just thinking about the food all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, trying to get beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: Denying food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to replace the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one thing that some people like to replace with is breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Breatharians.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I heard about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's another one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what's the difference then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you just take your breath?
[SPEAKER_00]: As a person of mind, you can't depend on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have... there is... the body is dependent on any nutriment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to say that it's, again, it's an illusion... Well, no, that doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a denial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Complete denial.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then... but breathing just air to nourish the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe some people can get better again, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's what... that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why we stop there, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you deny food, why don't you start denying breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what people did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what the Buddha tried to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, stop... stop breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, no, this is a completely wrong way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will never reach, well, freedom and liberation by doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what do you... like, you know, imagine...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, imagine the hardcore ascetic on a brink of death all the time, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Has already, you know, is his close friend, and we're the same, we have the same values.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he goes off and eats this milk rice given to him by a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... and he eats this bowl of probably quite delicious, tasty, healthy, fatty milk rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they see him doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, he took two oranges and said, where is your strength?
[SPEAKER_01]: He ate the milk ruts as a form of ascetic, when he realized, actually, no, this is going to be a waste of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to go the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because there's no wisdom in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just like a reaction in regards... and that's what it's... the simile of the vase.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine one entire vase.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it says.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first herd, basically, trapped and controlled by Mahārāja, and he does what he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, some other herd will actually see that, and they will recognize, oh, look, Mahārāja is actually there, and he traps people, and that is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what they do, they shun debate completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: In night, they run away from into the mountain when there is no pain, there is no mud, there is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, yeah, if you don't eat food, you will not be bothered by preferences in regard to food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just throw the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha himself said that so many times, which means then, that hurt eventually, when there isn't anything left in those mountains and they, you know, start starving, they go back down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the third herd sees the first group, sees the second group, and then realizes, well, what if we stay within the bait, and eat it wherever?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then we step ahead and say, well, then they start arguing over views.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might be, eh, living with wrong from sensuality, they start arguing over views and all kind of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Mahārāja finds that, so then the false head doesn't even argue over the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the principle in terms of sensuality is basically staying within the bait, because you have no choice, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by shunning the bait, you give power to the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, staying within the bait, but never ever eating it unwary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, imagine that for the rest of your life, whatever food you put in your mouth,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you eat that food?
[SPEAKER_01]: Very carefully, for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to put it in your mouth, piece by piece, bit by bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't let it go around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't lose mindfulness and just bite in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will rip your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, there is a bait, but you haven't been eating like a maniac, carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can feel it, you can pull it out, without actually harming yourself, you can eat the rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, for the rest of your life, you're going to eat everything you put in your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's all that happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that scene of crossing the desert, that's exactly what it says.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you really have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, we have to kill this child, because he won't survive either way, but at least he will give us a chance to survive, and then maybe have some more children, and then we'll implement and we'll come up with these children, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's obviously the best of the horrible scenario, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might quite like that child.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the taste of it, if you start eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because when you're starving, fried meat, but then you go, no, I must not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you still have to eat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how do you eat it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You eat it carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make sure you don't forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your only child that you just killed in order to survive, which means you won't forget the purpose why you're eating, which means you won't get carrots.
[SPEAKER_01]: And certainly, you won't resort to food for mere sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you won't have a problem eating once a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also seen as a... truly seen as something which will bring... will give you some sort of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: A noticeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a completely different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what you mean, but that's just a whole new level of wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not really worth addressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's just that it's such a... it is a very common and normal thing for most people.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... food is a nice thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And let us enjoy it together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let us have this... this taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... those are people who don't even have a concept of what the practice of any kind of wisdom would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just completely taking it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they're the first herd that doesn't even recognize that it's actually being trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say they're completely in control, but they don't even recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing you say to them will change that unless they themselves start seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, for goodness sake, people go as far as to mystify the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Christians, Kṛṣṇas, believe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you believe, oh, yeah, this fried up loaf of bread, whatever I'm eating now, is given to me by God, directed by God.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the God's body I'm eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Kṛṣṇa, through devotion, if I remember correctly, it's been ages ago,
[SPEAKER_01]: When I had a friend, a Christian, we would go for those lunches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we would go in there for the food, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a nice food, and he was a nice guy, but he wasn't really interested in whatever I was saying, so he just put up with it, so you can eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I remember, basically, the whole idea was
[SPEAKER_01]: This, this, like, the more you eat, the more of a, like, Krishna devotion you show, and it was just, it was, well, it's quite convenient, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hang, hang out, stuff yourself, and the God will love you more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or don't eat garlic, then you'll have no love.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, don't eat, don't eat specific things, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, that, that, that thing causes you heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a sexual organ causes
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being free from sensuality causes you heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taking vitamin B supplements, that's not the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only if you take vitamin B, you'll be, you know, you'll have lustful thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have lustful thoughts because you have a lustful body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vitamin B might remind you of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're not developing that, then it can be me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to have reproductive organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, blame the specific fools.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, don't blame those fools.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I'm not talking from the health perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking from a spiritual perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for those people, you know, that's why often spirituality is linked with health.
[SPEAKER_01]: With yogis or whoever else, I eat healthy food, my spirit is healthy, I'm good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you going to do when your body gets sick?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's old.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your whole life of spiritual development and bodily postures and stuff, gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: All your attainment is dependent on your healthy body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's not an attainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, not even there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even people who are young.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's a complete misplacement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's easy for people to do, because obviously the pure dhamma, the real dhamma itself is quite hard, subtle to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, do you see how many people could just have trouble grasping the idea of being mindful of an unreasoned thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, without resorting to some sort of, you know, scientific explanation, or saying it's constant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, just be mindful of a reasoned thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be mindful of an enduring a reasoned thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: A reasoned thing that endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the confusion is already set.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's the same thing, like, five seconds ago, and the thing now, that's not the same, but it is the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't, because it was five seconds...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a change within that same thing, but it's still the same thing, because you're still talking about it as the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's changing on a different level, and that's already mind-blowing, for most of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was, that was, you know, I think that was quite normal back in Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of authentic sort of recognition of, you know, they had, they didn't think they were in time, they didn't think time was constantly changing, and everything is in the flux.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had no notion such as those.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they would hear the dhamma sometimes first time, never before, it would immediately land.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had, they didn't have so many wrong views covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that is not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: With food, knowing that, or knowing that the body needs nutrient, concentrating on that, that can lead you far, just because you've got dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that preferences are secondary, and, by your concern, should be being mindful in regard to the need for the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if you eat everything you put in your mouth, as if I have a sharp fishbone for a metal hook, or something that if you bite, will break your tooth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be unable to eat it carelessly, if you cultivate that attitude, which means you will become unable to descend down into your belly as yours, and regard it as internal meat, which means you will stop going down into the central domain, where those pleasures can exercise powers over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you say is more powerful, food or sex?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sex would be more powerful, but food would be more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are hungry always, you won't have thoughts of sex.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sense, food is more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the pool of food, even when you are hungry, will never be as feverish and crazy as a pool of sex.
[SPEAKER_01]: A pool of sex is just a combination of all the pools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of the animals are pulling you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of the senses are intoxicated by just by the sexual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no single form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, a form of man besets a mind of a woman and a form of woman besets a mind of a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, a single sight, sound, smell, face, touch, as that of a man for a woman and a woman for a man.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, yeah, you have all five forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not as fundamental, which is why, obviously, it's completely unnecessary to be done at all, and it shouldn't be done at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: While the food you have, you know, you have to eat in an engagement, but then you have to sort of start separating, you know, eating the stuff around the bed, not with the bed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you say I can be mindful in all of them?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't know mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pure to
[SPEAKER_01]: To recognize mindfulness as an established thing, it's impossible to have that and the sexual desire, well, sexual pull that you said yes to, that you engaged at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha meant when he said it's impossible to engage in a sexual intercourse without being held by the essential perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without your mind being held by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's impossible to not perceive sensuality and engage in the actual act of sensuality, because that act is defined by the perceived sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the non-mindfulness, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The non-divided mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can know... you could try...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, obviously, persons having... if persons having sex, they can really be in present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're always in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Worth it, but it means... it means nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even know what the present moment is, then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is when people practice being in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just going...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing... nothing wrong being in the past moment or the future moment, if you're mindful of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But being able to strengthen your mind with mindfulness, or, let's say, strengthening... strengthening your mind, your head in mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to food, there will... Well, sexual?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, by not engaging in any form of sexual intercourse or activity, and then being mindful in regard to food, then that can lead you out of the sensual... sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, have your mind established above central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can be mindful as much as you want around the food, if you go... if you spend your day engaging in sexuality, sexual thoughts, and kind of cultivating, entertaining those, it won't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it does need to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to stop engaging in it beforehand, and then you can start developing the practice within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the viññāṇa and the sīla comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because both those, both those things again, you have a hungry stomach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, basically, demanding, senses demanding for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in this case, obviously, senses demanding for food, because they're hungry, and basically, uh, attending to their hunger by eating, providing pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's not necessarily food that you prefer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's already
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not mindful, that's already a hook, that's already a barrier.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, I mean, like, you can try running away from your preferences for as much as you want, but that's beside the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is to remain mindful through and through what you eat, whether you prefer it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even the food that you don't prefer, when you are hungry, it will provide you with simple pleasure of being food for your hungry stomach.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pleasure, it can be essential pleasure if you are unwary in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the food you put in your mouth is agreeable or not, because both have or might have a bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say that only food that you prefer has a bait, and you should avoid it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor does it say food that you hate has a bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says food has a bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Food might be a bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, actually, preference or not, it's completely second-hand thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: One should be rooted in practice, being rooted in that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the... well, there are... there wouldn't be preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were based on other preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were completely based on just pure pleasure, desire for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will fall off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now... because all of them require that attitude of non-mindfulness at the very root.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you start covering them up... and then... but then the other preferences won't necessarily fall off.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can still tell, no, this is a nice food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was not so nice food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was quite rough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that food smells really bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: I even have a gag reflex.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's, you know, that's nothing to do with... well, it's just a fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just about how those childish animals respond to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you eat it unmindfully, even the most horrible food,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the world, you still remain as enslaved, probably even more enslaved, because you think you're not enslaved, by avoiding preference, preferred food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, actually, you remain even, like, equally enslaved, but by thinking you're less enslaved, well, that adds another layer of slavery to you, that you yourself created.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's why, you know, you do have those extreme ascetics who would, you know, eat feces or who knows what.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just horrible, horrible stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they wouldn't be unwise at the very end of their life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, to be dispassionate towards food is not because food tastes bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because it's horrible food, but because it's... it's... it's there... Because Mara might have placed the bait in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That bait has nothing to do with agreeable or disagreeable food.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to do with Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, you don't actually blame the food, but you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you do, okay, so I just have to eat this food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then I'll just take great care.
[SPEAKER_01]: To avoid swallowing and biting and chewing into the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bait is a foreign object.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the body's business, food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not your business, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you have to attend to every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it means every day you need to be mindful of the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every day you need to be mindful of the trap and the snare.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the practice is basically about everyday mindfulness and that repetitive drilling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Drilling is quite a burden, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara is a bird, because he's relentless in having that bait placed in the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... but again, he has every right to do so, because the food belongs to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The food, the taste, and the tongue belongs to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sights and eyes belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sounds and ears belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because people take that which belongs to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara does what he wants with them, on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that he takes?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the eye and the sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the ear and the sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the nose and the smells.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, he, the senses, your senses actually belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he has every right to put whatever he wants in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's you who keeps biting careless and then hooking yourself like a mindless fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just basically... that's the deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person can complain about it, feel sorry for himself, but that's just how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will complain about it, feel sorry, because you're still refusing to give up your ownership of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still feel entitled to that, to your eyes and to the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because I was here first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.